{"tossups": [{"question": "This man\u2019s regent, Sophia Alekseyevna, listened to his meetings through a hole in his throne and led a revolt that forced this leader to disband the Streltsy. This man learned Dutch shipbuilding techniques on his \u201cGreat Embassy\u201d tour of Europe. He reorganized the Table of Ranks to weaken the Boyars, and he taxed long beards as part of his reform efforts. For ten points, name this westernizing Russian tsar.", "answer": "<b> Peter the Great</b> (or<b> Peter I</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This case\u2019s outcome was slammed in Byron White\u2019s dissent, who claimed it \u201cfashions and announces a new constitutional right.\u201d This case, in which Harry Blackmun cited a \u201ccompelling state interest\u201d as necessary to regulate privacy, affirmed a trimester framework. The initially anonymous plaintiff in this case, Norma McCorvey, later became a pro-life activist. For ten points, name this 1973 Supreme Court case that legalized abortion.", "answer": "<b> Roe</b> v. Wade", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s son Ernak became the last ruler of his people after another of this man\u2019s sons died at the Battle of Nedao. The<em> foederati</em> combined forces with Flavius Aetius and Theodoric to defeat this man at the Catalaunian Plains. In 452, Leo I successfully convinced this man to call off his invasion of Italy. The title<em> Flagellum Dei</em> was a epithet given to this man that translates to \u201cScourge of God.\u201d For ten points, name this leader of the Huns.", "answer": "<b> Attila</b> the Hun", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "One politician with this last name campaigned with a giant steel ball that rolled 5,000 miles across the country. Slogans written on that ball noted that \u201cOld Allegany [...] started the ball\u201d for a politician of this last name who defeated the incumbent Martin Van Buren, and that \u201cin \u201888 [...] we roll it on for Gallant Ben,\u201d his grandson. For ten points, give this surname shared by Benjamin and William Henry, a pair of 19th century Presidents.", "answer": "<b> Harrison</b> (accept Benjamin and/or William Henry<b> Harrison</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A composer from this country wrote a Rondo for<em> Abdelazar</em> that was used as the theme for a piece that taught instruments to children,<em> A Young Person\u2019s Guide to the Orchestra</em>. Another musician from this country wrote the forty-voice motet<em> Spem in Alium</em> and the melody to a<em> Fantasia</em> by Ralph [RAFE] Vaughan Williams. Thomas Tallis and Henry Purcell, were from, for ten points, what country where the folk song \u201cGreensleeves\u201d was supposedly written by King Henry VIII?", "answer": "<b> England</b> (accept<b> U</b>nited<b> K</b>ingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland; accept Great <b>Britain</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Life under this leader is depicted in the opening chapters of the novel<em> The Three-Body Problem</em>. This leader\u2019s wife wrote a series of Eight Model Dramas, including<em> The Legend of the Red Lantern</em> and<em> The Red</em> <em>Detachment of Women</em>. This ruler wrote that \u201cImperialism and All Reactionaries Are Paper Tigers\u201d in a book of quotations. For ten points, name this author of the<em> Little Red Book</em> who instituted the Cultural Revolution in China.", "answer": "<b> Mao Zedong</b> (accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "In this state, Native Americans established the regional capital of Tahlequah in a territory granted by the Treaty of New Echota. The Unassigned Lands were originally designated for Native Americans in this state, which was the destination of the Cherokees who migrated westward during the Trail of Tears. For ten points, name this state where eager participants in an 1889 land rush, called \u201cSooners,\u201d snapped up land between Norman and Tulsa.", "answer": "<b> Oklahoma</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Friar Diego Dur\u00b4an helped document the history of this civilization. In this empire\u2019s capital, many invaders drowned while carrying gold during an attack by Eagle Warriors. A man who helped conquer this empire betrayed Diego Velasquez and was aided by La Malinche [mah-lin-chay]. Montezuma II ruled, for ten points, what empire that was conquered after Hern\u00b4an Cort\u00b4es arrived in Tenochtitlan in modern-day Mexico?", "answer": "<b> Aztec</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man, while employed by his mentor Frankie Yale, was wounded by Frank Gallucio, a man who later served as his bodyguard. A group that investigated this man was chosen to be incorruptible by Eliot Ness; that group was disbanded after this man was arrested for tax evasion. Bugs Moran\u2019s men were killed in the St. Valentine\u2019s Day Massacre on the probable orders of, for ten points, what Chicago mobster nicknamed \u201cScarface?\u201d", "answer": "Alphonse \u201cAl\u201d<b> Capone</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A national park in this state filled with fairy chimneys, or \u201choodoos,\u201d is named for settler Ebenezer Bryce. In 2002, an Olympic torch relay passed under the Delicate Arch in this state\u2019s Arches National Park. This US state is the only one to have a majority of its population belonging to a single church. For ten points, name this Western U.S. state where, in 1847, Brigham Young founded Salt Lake City.", "answer": "<b> Utah</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This organization\u2019s popularity declined after one of its leaders, DC Stephenson, was found guilty of the murder of Madge Oberholtzer. Mary Phagan\u2019s murder inspired a resurrection of this group, which had been suppressed by Ulysses Grant\u2019s Force Acts. This group\u2019s first revival took place at Stone Mountain, where its members adopted clothing inspired by the film<em> Birth of a Nation</em> and burned a cross. For ten points, name this American terrorist white supremacist group.", "answer": "<b> K</b>u<b> K</b>lux<b> K</b>lan", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "David Lloyd George and this man were the \u201cTerrible Twins\u201d of the People\u2019s Budget. Harry Truman invited this man to speak at Westminster College, where he discussed the \u201csinews of peace\u201d and described postwar Europe as being split by an \u201ciron curtain.\u201d This politician promised his people his \u201cblood, toil, tears, and sweat\u201d in his first speech as British Prime Minister. For ten points, name this leader of the UK during World War II.", "answer": "Sir Winston (Leonard Spencer)<b> Churchill</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Nearly 10,000 people died in this sea when the<em> Wilhelm Gustloff</em> was sunk. In 1994, bad weather on this sea sank a cruise ferry, killing over 800 people. Ships heading west out of this sea pass through the heavily crowded Kattegat and Skagerrak. The Gulfs of Bothnia and Finland are arms of, for ten points, what European sea northeast of Germany that names the set of three countries on its eastern shore: Estonia, Latvia, and Lithuania?", "answer": "<b> Baltic</b> Sea", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "In 1478, a member of this family named Giuliano was stabbed 19 times during High Mass as part of a failed coup d\u2019etat. This family\u2019s coat of arms features six spheres called palle on a gold shield. Popes Clement VII and Leo X were members of this family, which was targeted by the aforementioned Pazzi Conspiracy. Michelangelo and Donatello were patronized by members of, for ten points, what powerful Italian family that included Cosimo and Lorenzo the Magnificent?", "answer": "<b> Medici</b> family (or the House of<b> Medici</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This country set up the Company of One Hundred Associates in 1627 to expand its empire, and it relied mostly on runners of the woods to expand its trading networks. Those</b> <b>trading networks were contested between this colonial power\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Huron allies and its</b> <b>rivals\u2019 Iroquois partners in the Beaver Wars. One of this country\u2019s writers dismissed its (*) </b>North American holdings as \u201ca few acres of snow\u201d in<em> Candide</em>. For ten points, name this country whose loss on the Plains of Abraham cost it much of North America, including Quebec.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> France</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this form of matrimony.", "answer": "<b> same-sex marriage</b> (or<b> gay marriage</b> or equivalents)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Leland Stanford sponsored a study of these animals that Eadweard Muybridge [\u201dedward my-bridge\u201d] used photography to undertake. Frederic Remington sculpted a bronze figurine of a (+)</b> <b>\u201cbuster\u201d on one of these animals. A sculpture with a nickname translating to\u201cHoneycat\u201d shows Erasmo da Narni on one of these animals, and was based on an earlier statue of the (*)</b> emperor Marcus Aurelius on military campaign. For ten points, name these animals which are typically featured with famous riders in equestrian statues.", "answer": "<b> horse</b>s (accept<b> Bronco</b> Buster)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>An admiral from this country daringly sailed up the Thames to wreak havoc during the Raid on the Medway. Roving privateers from this country called the Sea Beggars captured</b> <b>Brielle [BREEL] from the (+)</b> <b>Spanish in 1572, a turning point of the Eighty Years\u2019 War.</b> <b>This country\u2019s navy was led by admirals like Maarten Tromp and Michiel de Ruyter and supported by letters of marque issued by (*) </b> William the Silent. Indonesia was long ruled by an East India Company from, for ten points, what European maritime power ruled by the House of Orange?", "answer": "the<b> Netherlands</b> (accept the<b> Dutch</b> Republic; accept the<b> Dutch</b> Federation; accept the Republic of the (Seven) (United)<b> Netherlands</b>; accept the Kingdom of the<b> Netherlands</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Many years after this battle, Henry Dearborn sparked a public controversy by publishing a critique of his commanding officer\u2019s actions during it. A John Trumbull painting depicts</b> <b>Joseph Warren\u2019s (+)</b> <b>death during this battle. Forces led by William Prescott and Israel</b> <b>death during this battle. Forces led by William Prescott and Israel</b> <b>Putnam rebuffed a British attack at this battle. The order \u201cDon\u2019t (*)</b> <b>Putnam rebuffed a British attack at this battle. The order \u201cDon\u2019t (*)</b> fire until you see the whites of their eyes\u201d was probably given at, for ten points, what 1775 battle, mostly fought on Breed\u2019s Hill outside Boston?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Bunker Hill</b> (accept Battle of<b> Breed\u2019s Hill</b> before mentioned) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Judge Susan Webber Wright fined this man ninety thousand dollars for providing</b> <b>misleading testimony. During one election campaign, this man\u2019s (+) mistress Gennifer</b> <b>Flowers revealed their relationship on national television. A blue dress was among the</b> <b>evidence used to charge this man of (*)</b> perjury after he denied having sexual relations with Monica Lewinsky. For ten points, name this president who was the target of a failed impeachment campaign in the 1990s.", "answer": "William Jefferson \u201cBill\u201d<b> Clinton</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}